<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faithful and diligent servant of the Lord, blessed at the coming of his Lord as it was lately unfolded in a funeral discourse on the death of Mr. Thomas Cawton : and now on the earnest desire of the hearers published by H. Hurst.</title>
            <author>Hurst, Henry, 1629-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7692</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11800810</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11800810</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 538:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faithful and diligent servant of the Lord, blessed at the coming of his Lord as it was lately unfolded in a funeral discourse on the death of Mr. Thomas Cawton : and now on the earnest desire of the hearers published by H. Hurst.</title>
                  <author>Hurst, Henry, 1629-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cawton, Thomas, 1637-1677.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49378:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Faithful and Diligent SERVANT OF THE LORD, Bleſſed at the COMING OF HIS LORD. As it was lately unfolded in a <hi>Funeral Diſcourſe</hi> On the Death of Mr. <hi>THOMAS CAWTON.</hi> AND Now on the earneſt deſire of the Hearers Publiſhed by <hi>H. Hurſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi>-Chappel, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49378:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49378:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, and to thoſe who deſired the publiſhing of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT would be an indecorum, as cuſtom now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, to ſend abroad a diſcourſe, without direction where it may ſeek its entertainment: whether this be to be imputed to the great unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Readers, or to the unreaſonable multitude of Writers, it concerns me very little to enquire, and thee as little to know. To them I ſend it, who I hope intended honeſtly, when they deſired this plain diſcourſe might be publiſh'd; and though perhaps it might be weakneſs in me to let your deſires have this effect on me, yet it is no fault to wiſh it may, and to hope it will do thee good. It was a plain diſcourſe in my mouth, and it was needful it ſhould be ſo; and it is plain now in paper and Ink, becauſe I was deſir'd to publiſh what I preach'd: if it be ſomewhat more conciſe, it is not without reaſon (ſomewhat being proper enough to the Hearers, which might be leſs proper to Readers, who knew not thoſe circumſtances the Hearers were acquainted with). And you need quarrel the brevity of it no ſooner than you find you were at
<pb facs="tcp:49378:3"/>the end of it before you were willing. I am ſure I had an excellent pattern of fidelity and diligence in Gods Family, when I had his life in my eye, whoſe death was occaſion of this diſcourſe; I will not praeoccupate your Judgment, whether I have well commended the Duty to you, or encouraged you to the performance of it. I pray of you a ſerious and heedful Reading: and I pray to God that he would give you ſuch a heart as he requireth, ſuch a life of holy care to ſave your ſelves and others, that God may give you the bleſſedneſs of faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in life, at death, to eternity. That this may contribute to all theſe, prayeth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Souls Friend,</hi> H. H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RST.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April 20. 1677.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49378:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. XII. Ver. 43.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed is that Servant whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Think I need not give a Reaſon of my choice of this Text, when I have told you the occaſion of the words: If you will look into the Context, you will ſoon ſee how great agreement there is in it, to this mournful occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and that there was ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I ſhould fix here, where the beſt encouragement of faithful Servants is laid before us, and an example of ſuch an one is to be treated by us. Nor ſhall I need other reaſon to perſwade you to attend to what ſhall be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Lord, having exhorted his hearers to a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs and watchfulneſs, which becometh Servants whoſe Lord will certainly come, though they know not when, <hi>ver.</hi> 35, 36. And having encouraged them with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of bleſſedneſs, <hi>ver.</hi> 37, 38, in caſe they do attend diligently to this Duty, and perſevere in it unto his coming; and withall, propoſing it in ſo comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive a manner, that it did not appear whether it were ſpoken to all equally, or to ſome more than unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> either out of deſire to know his Duty, or out of curioſity to know his Lords mind, doth (as in ſome other caſes he did) make the enquiry, <hi>ver.</hi> 42, whether the Parable were ſpoken unto all, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49378:4"/>only to the Diſciples and Apoſtles, <hi>Lord, ſpeakeſt thou this unto us, or even unto all?</hi> unto which query, Chriſt gives ſuch an anſwer as doth more cloſely bind our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on us, and awakeneth all concerned in it, to ſee to it that they do their duty, be ready for their account, and wait for their bleſſedneſs; <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Who then is that faithful and wiſe Steward,</hi> &amp;c? Chriſt ſeems to have anſwered with a check to his curioſity, but with a direction to his and our willingneſs to our Duty; as if Chriſt had plainly told him, I ſpeak to as many as hope to be bleſſed by their Lord when he cometh, excluding none who pretend to the relation of Servants to the Lord, or to the hoped reward; who ſo would be found faithful in his work, and bleſſed for it; who ſo is either Servant or Steward, to him I ſpeak; and according to the proportion of the Talents and Truſt, I do adviſe to diligence and fidelity in their employs, and aſſure of bleſſedneſs to their fidelity. Be then your condition what it will, whether higher or lower in your Lords Family, if you are in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition faithful, and wiſe, and helpful to your fellow-Servants, and ſo continue to be till your Lord ſhall come, you are and ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant, whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words I ſhall, with your leave, briefly Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe: <hi>[Bleſſed],</hi> we ſo expreſs a good, comfortable, and deſirable ſtate: It is well with him that is bleſſed; and he is thus well, who is thus well doing, and found in it. [<hi>Is that Servant, whom,</hi> &amp;c.] This noteth the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of it, extending to all, and yet pointeth out the perſons, who are here put under the Character of bleſſedneſs; That Servant, though no more; That Steward or Ruler, if ſo much, is the perſon Chriſt ſpeaks of, who ſhall be bleſſed, when <hi>his Lord,</hi> who hath authority
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49378:4"/>and right to require and direct our obedience, who hath right of calling us to account, and of diſtributing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; when Chriſt ſhall come, then they who ſerved him faithfully, ſhall be bleſſed, and in a good condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[When he cometh]</hi> which referreth both to the time when, and to the manner how he cometh; at what time ſoever, or in what manner ſoever our Lord ſhall come, all his faithful ſervants ſhall be bleſſed, for they are found <hi>[ſo doing];</hi> which you muſt refer, partly to what was ſpoken more remotely in the Parable, and concerneth all according to the capacity in which they are, Servants in the Family; and partly to what was ſpoken in the foregoing verſe, where Stewards and Rulers in the Family, giving to the Family its portion of meat in ſeaſon, are deſcribed, and ſuppoſed to be found faithful and wiſe in this charge; and theſe are they who are ſo expreſly pronounced happy in their ſo doing. Briefly, this <hi>ſo doing,</hi> is doing the office of our places, and doing it according to the Rule there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wiſely, faithfully and diligently. The words thus opened, do lay in open view before us, 1. <hi>A Lord who will ſometime or other certainly come</hi> to ſee what his Servants are in their ſeveral places doing. 2. <hi>A bleſſedneſs or happy condition of ſome</hi> of thoſe Servants. 3. <hi>The Character of thoſe who ſhall be happy,</hi> which Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter is made up of the particulars mentioned diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>ver.</hi> 42, and ſumm'd up in the Text in <hi>ſo doing.</hi> Hence then paſſing by other particulars, I commend to your attention this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That whenſoever, and however our Lord ſhall come, all his Servants, eſpecially his Stewards, who have been wiſe, faithful, and diligent in his family, giving to all their portion in ſeaſon, ſhall be found in a good and happy ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not certain when or how our Lord will come;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49378:5"/>but whenever it is, or however it may be, they are Servants and Stewards in happy ſtate who are found fit for, and faithful in the Lords Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His condition is and ſhall be good, who is a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Great and good God.</hi> The meaneſt, and moſt ordinary Servants in the family being faithful, are bleſſed according to their capacities; the Stewards who are above ordinary Servants in their charge, abilities, and account, are alſo above them in their bleſſedneſs, when they are found faithful to their Lord. <hi>It is a good, and a great imployment to be a Servant: It is a better and greater thing to be a Steward in Gods Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Church of Chriſt. It is the beſt temper to be wiſe and faithful in diſcharge of either, as our Lord ſhall appoint to us and require of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in handling this Doctrine, that I may ſpeak fully to it, I ſhall deſire you with me to conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The time when our Lord cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The manner in which he cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Scriptures do aſſure us his faithful Servants are happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Wherein their happineſs doth conſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Why appropriated to ſo doing,</hi> i. e. to giving the Portion to each, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Why deferred until the coming of our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When theſe are diſpatched, the Doctrinal part will afford us profitable Application.</p>
            <p>Now to the firſt thing propoſed, I anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">General. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ds coming.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That our Lord in his coming doth not obſerve the ſame time towards all;</hi> he cometh ſooner to ſome, he ſtays longer to others; our experience and obſervation herein is an undeniable witneſs. Some Parents God hath taken away ſooner, and left in younger days both Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ows and fatherleſs Children: Some Preachers have h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the opportunities of Forty or Fifty years, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49378:5"/>have been called to their reſt at half that period. You know not how long God may continue you to yours, or them with you;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P. Martyr</hi> aged 63. <hi>H. Bulling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 50 years d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> aged 71. <hi>Guil. Fare</hi> lived 76 ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Biſhop <hi>Lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> lived years, and <hi>Gataker. Nicol. Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingius,</hi> ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 87. <hi>Theod. Beza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> aged 87. Dr. <hi>Chader<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 89. <hi>Pet. Nanniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> inſigni litera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura,</hi> viz. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> you had not been now mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under this loſs, if God had given to all his faithful Miniſters the ſame length of time for their work, to which ſome attended longer than others have lived. The years of labour to ſome exceeding by much the years of Life given to others. Thus 35 or 36 end the life, and of theſe, ſome 16 or 17 years end the Labours of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God; yet he dyed not the youngeſt Miniſter that ever yet dyed. But the unaccountable variety here bids me forbear to enquire farther into it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That our Lords coming is according to his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined purpoſe:</hi> Our times for life and ſervice are in Gods hand; they are reſerved with him, and he will come in his own time. Were our times in other hands, we might be unſeaſonably hurried too ſoon out of Life and Labour, by unkind hands of ill-willers; or detained too long by the unwillingneſs of our Friends to part with us. But our Lord hath appointed, and will keep his own ſet-time to come to us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There can no meaſures be given beforehand, what time our Lord will take to come to us in.</hi> Nor may we expect any ſuch Rules from any by which to gueſs how long it will be ere our Lord will come to you, or me; Thouſands have within our time and obſervation (if we had heeded it) been ſummoned, when all about them have thought they might have continued much longer. Parents have loſt their Children, Wives have loſt their Husbands, and People have been deprived of their Paſtors on a ſudden, when no ſuch cala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y was fear'd. Our Lord hath not made an hour to come ſure to any of us, or inveſted us with a Right to another ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding moment. Our rule is, <hi>Work now,</hi> attend on the preſent buſineſs God lays before us, for our <hi>Lord comes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49378:6"/>at an hour we know not of,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.42, ſooner or later; expected, or unexpected; ſeaſonably to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, or unſeaſonably to our Friends, Relations, and Churches grief; we cannot foretel. Sure we are, he cometh not to all at one age, nor to any in any time but his own; nor with certain fore-warnings of weeks, or days, or hours; he hath no where told us he will ſtay a day longer for the youngeſt of us: <hi>It is enough that he doth aſſure us, if we are faithful in our places, and ſerve him, we ſhall be bleſſed in ſo doing.</hi> And as the time is thus various, ſo in the ſecond place, His manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is various; of which next.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>The ner of our is coming.</hi>
               </note> There are five ſeveral ways wherein the Lord is pleas'd to come toward us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He cometh in publick afflictions, and general cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities upon Kingdoms, or Nations, or People, among which many of his faithful ſervants dwell, and are with others oftentimes involved in their troubles and ſorrows:</hi> When the Lord did call (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 50) his Saints together, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, he tells us <hi>a fire ſhall devour before him;</hi> and this is the effect when God ſhall come, and not keep ſilence. Of ſuch a coming <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh in theſe words, <hi>The Lord ſhall come out of his place to puniſh the inhabitants of the earth,</hi> Iſa. 26.21. The faithful Servants of God inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the earth with others, may thus feel the caſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory indignation of their Father. And in his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick lofty ſtrains, the ſame Prophet doth lively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this coming of the Lord, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 verſes, Who is repreſented coming with the <hi>weapons of his indignation,</hi> verſ. 5, <hi>And the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction cometh,</hi> verſ. 6, <hi>To lay the land deſolate,</hi> verſ. 9, which was indeed accompliſht in its time on <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Jews after they had rejected Chriſt, and crucified him; yet then at this coming, thoſe that were faithful, were found in a good Condition; they were bleſſed who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49378:6"/>ſerved the Lord, and prepar'd for his coming; though this be not the coming chiefly meant in the Text, yet the Doctrine is ſound in this regard.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sometime the Lord cometh in that manner, that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular families or perſons are found out by the rod and corrections.</hi> Lev. 20.5, God ſpeaks of cutting off a houſe or perſon. <hi>Dent.</hi> 29, 18, 19. God warneth perſons in a Family, and the Family too; now if ſuch do not take warning, but provoke him, he will in his own time come to correct or puniſh ſuch a perſon or family: of this manner of proceeding are we to underſtand that of 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30, 31, and <hi>cap.</hi> 3.13. When God doth thus viſit perſons, or families, he is properly enough ſaid to come againſt them, and <hi>in ſuch caſes</hi> ſtill it holdeth true, <hi>Thoſe ſervants of God who are faithful in their ſervice to God, are bleſſed, or in a good condition.</hi> So <hi>Eli</hi> was, though he ſmarted under the Rod; and <hi>David</hi> comforted himſelf in the proſpect hereof, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5, <hi>though his houſe ſhould not grow;</hi> though ſevere corrections and rebukes ſhould cauſe the Beauty of his houſe to wither; yet God would give him the Covenant-ſalvation, it ſhould be well with him, in caſe of ſuch coming: though the Text leſs intend it, the Doctrine is both true and uſeful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sometime the Lord cometh to ſearch and try mens ſtate, and conſcience is awakened to make enquiry, and to diſcover them to themſelves.</hi> While God ſtands as at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, men are ſecure; but when he cometh by his Word and Spirit, and commands an admiſſion, he ſets up that light within the mans ſoul that diſcovers what he hath done, what he may expect, and what he farther muſt do. <hi>The word is ſharp as a two-edged ſword, and ſearcheth the reins,</hi> Heb. 4.12. And thus the ſecrets of mens hearts are diſcovered, when God cometh with his word, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25, among men. When <hi>God heweth men by his prophets,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49378:7"/>and maketh his judgments as the light,</hi> Hoſ. 6.5, then he cometh into the heart and conſcience. Now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Faithful and Diligent are in a good condition, when their hearts do not condemn them, when they know God will not condemn them. But oh the ſad condition of thoſe that dare not look themſelves in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves! that are ſelf-condemned, and afraid to know what God diſcovereth at ſuch coming! The Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> who did not obey the Command of the Lord, could not endure the Prophets, or their word. But <hi>Joſiah</hi> who was faithful to God, can bear ſuch a ſearching word, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.19. &amp; 27. <hi>ver.</hi> Who deſire to be faithful to God, they dare abide this coming; it doth diſcover their ſincerity, and declare them happy. In this caſe (though not directly intended by the Text) it holdeth true, All Gods faithful Servants and Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards are found in a good and happy ſtate. But next, which is that coming intended chiefly in the words and Doctrine:</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>When Death is the Meſſenger God ſendeth to let us know he is coming to us, when he fetcheth us from amidst men, and cometh to take account of each of us;</hi> each man by man, thus viſited, is either more or leſs happy, as he is found more or leſs faithful and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent at this coming of the Lord; this is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of which by concurrent vote of our Interpreters the Text doth ſpeak, as alſo doth its Parallels, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. <hi>ver.</hi> 42, 43. and <hi>Mark</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 34, 35, 36. of which I ſay the leſs, becauſe it paſſing with ſo general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, needs not much proof. But,</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, <hi>The Lord cometh in his Glory and Majeſty to raiſe the dead, and to Judg all men.</hi> They who now do, ſhall not eternally ſleep in the duſt; God will come and call them out of their beds: <hi>The Lord Jeſus will deſcend with the voice of the Trump,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49378:7"/>and the dead ſhall hear and riſe, to the great, general and laſt judgment.</hi> Thus <hi>he cometh to judg the world</hi> (Pſal. 96.13, and 98.9,) <hi>with righteouſneſs, and the people with equity.</hi> Places that, ſpeaking of the Kingdom of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> do include this Royal procedure which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate his miniſterial Government. When he cometh (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7,) <hi>in view of every eye, for every eye ſhall ſee him when he thus cometh;</hi> or as 'tis deſcribed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23, 24, 25, At this coming the Faithful diligent Servant is in good ſtate. Briefly then, <hi>Whether our Lord come ſooner or later to try the heart by his word, or families by his Rod, or Nations, as he did try the Jews by more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick calamities; In theſe caſes the moſt faithful of his Servants and Stewards are in the most ſafe and bleſſed ſtate; but when he cometh as the judg of all men to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular judgment, calling each man by death; and to the general judgment, calling all men before him; He, and he only is in a good and bleſſed ſtate, who is found to have been faithful and diligent in his Stewardſhip and Service within the Houſe and Family of God, giving to each what portion of meat is due to them.</hi> Which is</p>
            <p>In the third place now to be proved by the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Teſtimony of the Scriptures.
<note place="margin">3. Gen. <hi>Proofs of the Doctrine.</hi>
               </note> Where we find all faithful and diligent Servants, and Stewards eſpecially, pronounced bleſſed and happy in their attendance to the work of doing good to all as they are able, and therein ſerving their Lord, and waiting for his coming. So <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord:</hi> Death is the greateſt, as well as laſt Enemy to our life; yet if that natural life be ſpent for the Lord, and we dye in him, we are bleſſed; for ſuch mens Works do follow them, and they reſt from their Labours. Now certainly leſſer troubles, and lighter afflictions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not render him or her unhappy, whom Death found and left in a bleſſed ſtate; ſo that to work thoſe works
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49378:8"/>which we would have to follow us, and to dye in the Lord, as they prove our Fidelity, ſo they do prove our Felicity, and at once prove us good Chriſtians, and in good ſtate. Again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34, 35, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are ſuch who fed, cloathed, harboured, viſited, and refreſhed thoſe in the Lords Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, though the leaſt of his Family, <hi>verſ.</hi> 40, which was as much a Duty to them who could do it, as it was uſeful to others for whom it was done: Now they are declared happy ones, who had thus, according to their opportunity Miniſtred unto others. And much more will they appear bleſſed, who have faithfully directed thirſty Souls to the Fountain of living Waters, hungry Souls to the Bread of Life, naked Souls to the white Robes, wandring Souls to the reſt of Souls. Again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21, <hi>Not he that ſaith, Lord, Lord, but he that doth the Will of my heavenly Father, &amp;c.</hi> not a fruitleſs profeſſion, but a faithful obedience; not an unactive complement, but a diligent fulfilling the Will of our Lord, is at laſt a bleſſing to us; he is in a good ſtate indeed, whoſe Lord doth reward his Service with an entrance into, and enjoyment of eternal life in Heaven. And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can alter it to him, who altereth not his courſe of Faithfulneſs and Diligence. Such an one is (<hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22,) <hi>Bleſſed in his deed:</hi> now who is bleſſed in doing his work, can never be in ill-ſtate whilſt he is doing it; and he is in better ſtate when the work done is rewarded: <hi>whoſe work is his happineſs, cannot but be happy, whilſt he attends his work;</hi> and this is the caſe of all diligent and ſincere obſervers of Gods Commandments,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>The keeping them is a great reward.</hi> Chriſtians conſider it, if <hi>glory, honour, immortality, and eternal life,</hi> can be a bleſſedneſs to us, we are aſſured of this, <hi>For every ſoul that doth good</hi> (as God requireth) <hi>whether Jew or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile,</hi> Rom. 2.13. <hi>There is a crown of righteouſneſs</hi> (2 Tim.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49378:8"/>4.8. for St. <hi>Paul</hi> who had fought a good fight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, but if it were limited to his perſon, none could rejoyce herein with aſſurance for themſelves; or were it limited to his excellent qualifications, and unparallel'd diligence, few or none of us could argue our own right hereby; therefore it is added, <hi>not for me only, but for all that love his appearing.</hi> It is then unqueſtionable, that when the Lord ſhall come by Death and particular Judgment to any of us; and when he ſhall come in the general Judgment to us all, every faithful and diligent Servant ſhall be bleſſed. And the bleſſedneſs of that future ſtate, will as much make and keep every ſtate here in our way to it, good and happy, as gains of thouſands yearly will make and keep him rich who loſeth ſome farthings or pence now and then. Thus in general, the common and ordinary Servants find their diligence and fidelity to be their happineſs; <hi>Stewards and Miniſters of the grace of God find it much more their happineſs to have been faithful and diligent.</hi> So the Holy Ghoſt ſeems to ſpeak for encouragement to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Smyrna, Rev.</hi> 2.10. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel</hi> are mentioned, <hi>who did handle the word of God faithfully, and commended themſelves to the conſciences of men,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>Who did preach not themſelves, but Chriſt,</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Who were troubled on every ſide,</hi> verſ. 8. Of theſe it is ſaid, that <hi>light and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary afflictions work for them a far more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternal weight of glory,</hi> verſ. 17, 18. The ſhare Miniſters ſhall have in anſwer to the diligence and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their Labours, ſhall be greater than the ſhare of common or ordinary Chriſtians at the coming of him who is Lord to them all. When each Believer hath his Crown, and all their joys are full, then are thoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers an acceſſion to the glory and joy of their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diligent Miniſters, who labour'd for their Converſion, and helped forward their final and eternal ſalvation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49378:9"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19, 20. And once for all, that of <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3, <hi>Who turn many to righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the firmament, &amp;c.</hi> Each faithful Miniſter ſhall have his <hi>Aureola,</hi> golden Ornament added to his Crown: though all the faithful Servants of the Lord ſhall be as the ſtars, yet one ſtar differeth from another; the moſt bright and glorious will be thoſe who were on earth the ſtars that Chriſt held in his right hand, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1.</p>
            <p>Theſe Scriptures, with others, which might be added, do confirm the bleſſed future ſtate of faithful and diligent Servants, and Stewards, who in the Lords family attend to their work, and ſerve the Lord by their affording what help they can to all; and in proportion to their truſt and fidelity, ſhall be their happineſs at Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And in the mean time, in what ever way of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections or judgments the Lord may come to others, and to them while they are among others, and are liable to troubles; yet they ſhall be found bleſſed in publick troubles, bleſſed in private troubles, bleſſed under per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal trials, at death more, in the reſurrection moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, happy, and in good ſtate in all theſe caſes.</p>
            <p>Now wherein this bleſſedneſs conſiſteth, is the fourth propoſed head of our diſcourſe, to which your attention is now deſired, that you may be throughly affected with this undoubted truth, and be brought to a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for fidelity and diligence according to your Talents, and may at laſt have a larger meaſure of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that future bleſſedneſs, which I thus range be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.
<note place="margin">4. Gen. <hi>What the bleſſedneſs of faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The faithful and wiſe Servant of the Lord is bleſſed in the pardon of his ſins, and culpable blemiſhes, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termix with his ſervices.</hi> He that will be ſo wiſe for, and faithful to his fellow Servants, as to perſwade, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, encourage and help them to ſerve the Lord, cannot be ſuppos'd will not be wiſe for himſelf, or unfaithful to
<pb facs="tcp:49378:9"/>himſelf, or neglect to ſue out a Pardon for his known and unknown infirmities: The good man <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> cap. 13.22, <hi>ſought this pardoning Grace from the greatneſs of Gods mercy, when he reflected upon the great ſervices he had done for God and his Church. David,</hi> the man after Gods own heart, <hi>joins</hi> this <hi>ſuit for Pardon, to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts for guiding in the ways of God,</hi> to which he was fully addicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.4, 5, 6. and in midſt of troubles he ſueth for the ſame mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. <hi>ver.</hi> 15.16, 17, 18. <hi>When his feet were in the net,</hi> v. 15. <hi>when deſolate,</hi> v. 16. <hi>when troubles were enlarged into diſtreſſes,</hi> v. 17. Then he pray'd that God would forgive all his ſin. So the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Church, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, <hi>prays, and God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he will do it,</hi> ver. 4. And ſo <hi>Micah</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 18.19. Now this maketh any condition good and ſafe: <hi>The man whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven,</hi> Pſal. 32. ver. 1, <hi>is in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place and in every condition a ſafe and happy man.</hi> God who pitieth infirmities, pardoneth them where he finds ſincerity in his Servants. He that faithfully warns another, and calls on him to repent, and ſeek his Pardon; he that faithfully endeavours to engage others to do their Duty, and ſeek for mercy, is a man whom God hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, ſo as to enſure the bleſſedneſs for himſelf which he perſwades others to look after. Parents, Husbands, Wives, Friends and Miniſters, who heartily deſire and labour to get others into the ſervice of God, on terms and encouragements ſufficient to prevail with them, are indeed the perſons whom we muſt in charity believe are pardoned. I ſhould think he were pardoned who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Grace of his Prince, who perſwaded to all due Allegiance for future, and urged his fellow Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſue for Pardon of what had been ill and unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done already. It is certain the faithful are forgiven and bleſſed therein, though perhaps they have not ſenſe of it, or we evidences to prove it of them. Now no condition
<pb facs="tcp:49378:10"/>can come on ſuch a man, to render him miſerable or in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſtate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The bleſſedneſs of ſuch faithful and diligent ones does lie in that gracious acceptance which God doth afford to them for all their ſincere and willing obedience,</hi> though imperfect in it ſelf, unſucceſsful to others, and altogether unprofitable to God. It is a bleſſed thing <hi>to be accepted with God;</hi> this is <hi>Heaven upon Earth;</hi> this is <hi>Heaven af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we leave Earth.</hi> The Lord rejecteth none that he hath fitted for, and who are faithful in his charge: This was a bleſſing that <hi>David</hi> intreated of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.14, <hi>Let the meditations of my heart, and the words of my mouth be acceptable in thy ſight,</hi> &amp;c. This gracious acceptance did in <hi>Davids</hi> troubles counter-balance the grieviouſneſs of his troubles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8, with <hi>ver.</hi> 13. He could bear the reproach of enemies, when he knew his prayer ſhould be acceptable unto his God. No Courtier deſpis'd by Rebels is ſo happy in his Prince's Favour, and free acceſs to his Prince's Perſon, as ſuch diligent and faithful Servants are in their acceſs to, and acceptance with their God. You may gueſs at what I ſay by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment <hi>Cain</hi> (of men one of the worſt) had of Gods refuſing to accept him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. It caſt him down, and fill'd him with trouble. <hi>No condition is uneaſy to a ſoul that enjoys Gods Favour; for it is better than life,</hi> Pſal. 63. ver. 3. and every condition is dark and doleful without his favour. What is Hell, but a place where hopeleſs Souls are under the inconceivable Tortures of an eternal rejection and ſeparation from God? What is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but a glorious, free, full and eternal ſtate of nearneſs to God, and of favour with him? This acceptance is the great bleſſing God hath promiſed to ſuch as ſerve and love him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.7. <hi>It is the ſum of all we obtain through Chriſt, in whom we are accepted with God,</hi> Eph. 1. ver. 6. Matt. 25. ver. 21, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant,</hi> is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49378:10"/>enough to make us bleſſed now; <hi>enter thou into the joy of thy Maſter</hi> is fulneſs of the future bleſſedneſs. In every ſtate, and at the coming of the Lord, thus bleſſed is the good Servant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>This Bleſſedneſs of the faithful and good Servant, doth lie partly in the peace and tranquility of his mind, perſwaded that now ſin is pardoned and his duties are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: every condition ſhall at laſt give place to what is beſt, and all ſhall work together for good to him;</hi> though va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious troubles do tols him, yet they (like rowling waves) carry the Ship toward the Harbour. It is well with him, becauſe he knoweth the knife which lanceth him, doth not make him a Sacrifice under avenging Juſtice. And though he is corrected, yet it is under the hand of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is not deſtroyed by the hand of an Executioner. He is ſatisfied <hi>that it is good for him that he hath been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,</hi> Pſal. 119. ver. 67, 71, 75. When he ſuffers with others, he ſeeth he needed it; ſo all appears ſeaſonable, neceſſary and profitable to him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6, <hi>We are in heavineſs for a ſeaſon if need be, and for our profit,</hi> Heb. 12. ver. 10. It is bleſſed to be refined, and God doth by his coming intend this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48. <hi>ver.</hi> 10, <hi>That he may chuſe them before others.</hi> Now this conſidered, the faithful Servants of God do account their condition good, for that it is always tending to, and ſhall at laſt end in what is beſt for them: It is on the increaſe towards full happineſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The faithful and good Servants happineſs doth partly conſiſt in that ſupport which his Lord giveth to him under his burthens; while he ſubmits to the will of his Lord waits for him, and doth his Duty, he is ſupported by the preſence of his Lord:</hi> He ſinketh not, becauſe the Lord uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18. When <hi>Davids</hi> feet did well nigh ſlip, the Lords mercy held him up. It is an unutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able variety of helps that God affordeth to his faithful
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49378:11"/>ones, they are very ſecret, unexpected, ſtrong and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, many times beyond the belief of ſtrangers, and the hope of thoſe who receive them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.2, <hi>In midſt of Rivers and waters, in midſt of fire and flames;</hi> if God promiſe to be with us, we may account our condition good and ſafe; for his preſence ſhall ſave us from Rivers, that they do not overflow us, and from Fire, that it kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not on us. Now thus ſafe and good is the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every faithful Servant of God, he is pardoned, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, bettered, and ſupported ſtill, The <hi>Angel of Gods preſence is with him, and ſaveth him,</hi> Iſa. 63. ver. 9. He is bleſſed whom God will ſave, whom God will ſupport. It is ſad to be left ſinking under our burthens; but to be ſupported under them, is next to a bleſſed freedom from them, or next to a life above them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>However, it may be death ſhall be the ſad conſequence of a faithful and diligent Servants ſufferings with others; yet he is in this caſe bleſſed too: For he might die in peace and joy; he doth at leaſt die in ſafety, and free from danger of ſuture evils.</hi> It is poſſible a good Servant may die under fears, but he doth not die under danger of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; <hi>Who walk in their integrity, enter into their Reſt,</hi> Iſa. 57. ver. 2. Though Death be an enemy, it is laſt to a child of God: Stewards and Servants though faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diligent, yet they muſt die; but after death there is no other enemy, all is then ſafe to them: they paſs by Death to the enjoyment of the love of their Lord, to be filled with that love which is inconceivable, and poſſeſs that love which is eternal; from which, <hi>Nothing can ever ſeparate them,</hi> Rom. 8. ver. 37, 38. <hi>thus death is theirs,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. ver. 22. Now that is a bleſſed ſtate indeed which is ſo full of ſafety: How do dying men acknowledg this! when Death brings no danger with it, we are happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: This <hi>Balaam</hi> wiſh'd for, though he never attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. The untruſty and ſlothful Servant is unhappy in
<pb facs="tcp:49378:11"/>his death, becauſe he dyeth under greateſt danger, he dyeth an evil and wicked Servant; the good Servant dyeth as ſafe as he can wiſh, and as happy as he can be made. Which will appear in the</p>
            <p>Sixth thing, wherein the bleſſed ſtate of ſuch doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt: <hi>They paſs after death immediately into an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable glory, where their ſouls purifi'd from all ſin, and made perfectly holy, enjoy a bleſſed, though not a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated glory:</hi> they are <hi>in the joys of their maſter;</hi> they live in the ſight of their glorifi'd redeemer, triumph over ſin and temptation; aſſured of the future reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their bodies, without tediouſneſs of a delay wait for it; <hi>they poſſeſs their building of God, their houſe not made with hands, which is eternal in the heavens,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>They are before the throne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14. Thus bleſſed in life, in death, after death, are the faithful Servants of the Lord. And yet, this is not all, there is</p>
            <p>A ſeventh thing, part of their bleſſedneſs, which, when their Lord cometh, they ſhall enjoy, <hi>that is, the reſurrection of their bodies in a glorious conformity to the glorifi'd body of their redeemer.</hi> When the Lord of theſe Servants and Stewards we ſpeak of, ſhall come and awaken all out of their beds of duſt; His good Servants, whoſe bodies were ſown in diſhonour, ſhall receive their bodies raiſed in honour: thoſe bodies which were ſown mortal and weak, ſhall be raiſed immortal, and in ſtrength, fit to be the eternal habitation of immortal ſouls; and both ſoul and body united, ſhall ever live in a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, regular and ſinleſs harmony and friendſhip. You that admire the unparallel'd beauties of mortal creatures, and judg That their happineſs, which is your envy or wiſh; withdraw your eye, and look to the Grave, whence the rareſt beauties are at laſt to riſe, whence the firmeſt ſtrength, the moſt deſirable activity, and the ſpiritfulleſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49378:12"/>vigor. And then ſay whether you can think them leſs than <hi>bleſſed, who have their part in this Reſurrection,</hi> to allude to that of Saint <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing ſhall ever be able to hinder them from this, which though exceeding great, is yet followed with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part neceſſary to their happineſs; which is,</p>
            <p n="8">8thly, <hi>A publick, ſolemn and full declaration of their abſolution from the charge which men or Devils, in their accuſation of them, would load them with; nay, the charge wherewith the Law would burthen them, ſhall be fully and ſolemnly taken off:</hi> when they ſhall be <hi>juſtified</hi> before men and Angels, <hi>from all that from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of Moſes,</hi> Act. 13.38, which ſhall be when our Lord ſhall proceed in Judgment towards all, when according to the order of the Reſurrection, thoſe that are Chriſts, ſhall be firſt called, judged and abſolved; when according to the order of the Parable, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.34, Thoſe ſhall be adjuged to glory firſt, who fed the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, cloathed the naked, took into their houſes thoſe that were ſtrangers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I doubt not, you'l confeſs is a great happineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: well, when our Lord cometh, thus happy ſhall all his faithful and diligent Servants be, who in life laid out themſelves in labour for the Lord, who in death reſt from their labours, and whoſe labours follow them into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be examined, pardoned and rewarded according to the riches of Grace.</p>
            <p n="9">9thly, Our Lord, when he cometh, will add another thing to their happineſs: <hi>They ſhall then with him, as aſſeſſors and approvers of his righteous proceeding with the reſt of the world, ſit Judges of the world;</hi> of this we are aſſured, <hi>Jude</hi> 14, <hi>The Lord cometh with</hi> (or in midſt of) <hi>ten thouſand of his Saints to Judg,</hi> &amp;c. Of this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks more clearly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2, <hi>The Saints ſhall judg the world:</hi> Nay, more, <hi>we ſhall judg Angels,</hi> ſaith the
<pb facs="tcp:49378:12"/>Apoſtle. <hi>This honour have all his Saints;</hi> and in this they are bleſſed: and this is enough to make every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition good to them, until the glorious coming of their Lord, until they are thus advanced: In a word, Chriſt ſeems to promiſe to his, who are more than the ordinary Servants in his Family, a more than ordinary degree of this Honour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 28, 29, 30. with <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.28. I will not enquire how far faithful Stewards and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are herein, next to the Apoſtles, concerned: It is well for them, their faithfulneſs to ſouls ſhall then be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted and honoured.</p>
            <p n="10">10thly and laſtly, <hi>Chriſt our Lord, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father Judg of all, will, when the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Judgment is finiſhed, and the wicked world is caſt into Hell, thrown into the place of Torment, where their worm dieth not, where the fire is not quenched; Then Chriſt will take all his faithful ones, and paſs with them into the inconceivable and eternal Glory of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, brought to the fulleſt degree of greatneſs and Majeſty that is foretold to us.</hi> When they ſhall ever be with the Lord, and behold his Glory; when they ſhall be like to him whom they ſee, and be filled with that Glory that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on them; when all the Saints of God, and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhall be amaſſed into one great and general aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and all orderly ranged before the throne of God, and the Lamb miniſtring in ſinleſs praiſes, love and adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ever.</p>
            <p>Now certainly, could you and I lift up our eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this illuſtrious aſſembly; could we view them there, we ſhould ever be ſatisfied, That diligence in, and faithfulneſs to the ſervice of our Lord, according to our capacity, now is, and will, at the coming of our Lord, appear to be as much our comfort and happineſs, as it is our Duty, and ought to be our care. Oh then, let us conſider, <hi>What it is to be acquitted from guilt: What to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49378:13"/>be approved and rewarded: What 'tis to be bettered by all providences: What to die in ſafety at laſt: Is not this to be bleſſed? Is not this to die the death of the righteous?</hi> Why Chriſtians, your faithfulneſs and diligence ſhall ſo be found, and ſo end, if you continue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do we believe a glory ſucceeds our death, a reſurrection our burial, a publick abſolution our being judged? ſhall we ſit aſſeſſors, approvers, and witneſſes to the Great Judg, and paſs with him into glory everlaſting?</hi> And ſhall not our unwearied diligence and faithfulneſs exerciſed in his Service, prove we believe the truth, and expect this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit hereof? I hope now you will be leſs moved with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent difficulties, and more fixed for future diligence in ſerving the Lord, and doing good to his Family, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here by giving the Portion of meat in ſeaſon; in which appears the wiſdom and fidelity of Servants and Stewards, and to which bleſſedneſs is annexed and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated in the Text. The Reaſon whereof, is the fifth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral head of diſcourſe, and which we ſhall now briefly touch upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Wiſdom and faithfulneſs in Servants and Stewards,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. <hi>Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ted, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> of,</hi> &amp;c.</note> are the beſt qualifications, and compriſe all that a Lord and Maſter requireth, or need require in them:</hi> for wiſdom makes them meet for ſuch a truſt, and faithfulneſs encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth their Lord to truſt them. And both theſe appear in their obſerving what is fit for each perſon and ſeaſon, and applying to both accordingly. So when Fathers know what is fit for Children, and Maſters know what is fit for Servants, and Miniſters for their people, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly inſtruct, reprove, warn, encourage, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them: Here is both the widom and fidelity requiſite to a good Servant; and <hi>the Lord, who intends in the Text to oblige us to all that good Servants and Stewards ſhould do, hath thus cloſely couched all our Duty in this comprehenſive phraſe.</hi> So the bleſſedneſs is appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49378:13"/>not to a ſingle Duty, but to the univerſal dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent diſcharge of all our Duty; which is ſummed up in this giving to each other our Portion of meat in ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thus we are ſeaſonably minded of that great and neceſſary duty, which the laſt and worſt age of the world doth neglect;</hi> we are minded of giving mutual help and furtherance to each other in the way of Holineſs and Obedience. Our diſputing, quarrelling, cenſuring, and condemning age, is ready to turn one another out of the way, to diſpute each other out of the truth, and to quarrel each other for doing their duty, inſtead of help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other to do it: But this little becomes Servants and Stewards in the ſame Family; this is no part of their wiſdom or fidelity; Chriſt knew we ſhould (unto his coming) need each others help, and hath therefore ſo commended it as our wiſdom and fidelity, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the diſcharge of it by this large reward. Let us then have ſo much reaſon to ſee the excellency of the duty and temper, and ſo much Religion before God, and love to our ſelves, as to get this temper that we may do the duty, and receive the reward, and be at laſt bleſſed with thoſe we helpt towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This giving the portion of meat in ſeaſon: <hi>This charitable benificence, puts a great honour upon Religion, and commends it to others:</hi> And Chriſt doth therefore expect we ſhould thus adorn our Profeſſion; and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth us to it, by ſuch a declaration of the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe who attend this duty. A wiſe, faithful, and diligent Phyſitian credits his Profeſſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth men, that it is very uſeful and profitable to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. A Chriſtian of ſuch a temper in Chriſtianity, and ſo exerciſing himſelf to do this comprehenſive good in his place, doth as much convince the world, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb facs="tcp:49378:14"/>is of all Profeſsions moſt uſeful to mankind, who are by it helped forward in the arduous and important affairs of eternity.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thus we are awakened to greater watchfulneſs over our ſelves and others, and minded of obſerving, laying hold on, and improving opportunities; which, though we are ſo engaged not to let ſlip, yet we too too often let fall quite out of our own hands: and that becometh for ever impoſſible to us, which once might have been eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effected by us.</hi> Time is not eaſily redeemed, but opportunities are more difficultly recovered, and for moſt part once ſlipt, and for ever loſt: Well then, might ſuch Emphaſis be laid on this Duty of giving a portion in ſeaſon, that all might be awakened to heed what op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities are in their hand. Oh conſider it, I beſeech you, Parents for your Children, Husbands for your Wives, Maſters for your Servants, elder ones for the younger, and Miniſters for their People; you cannot always live, they muſt dye, and neither can give or receive helps when death ſwallows up your opportunities. You'l never hear him catechiſing, preaching, praying, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, who now reſts in his grave; and you are not ſure you ſhall ever have ſuch another. How heedful ſhould we be then to receive our portion when offered, and to offer it to others while we may; and be ſo found prepared for the reward which is promiſed to theſe good Servants, but is reſerved until the coming of our Lord: The reaſon of which delay or adjourning of our happineſs is the ſixth General branch of our diſcourſe, and now cometh to be conſidered. And ſo,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gen. <hi>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſedneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>y reſerved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> laſt coming,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeaſons and manner of our Lords coming before Death and Judgment, are notable diſcoveries of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs of ſinners, and therefore do by a neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence manifest the happineſs of the ſervants of God;</hi> Though light is always pleaſant, yet it was moſt pleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:49378:14"/>in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> when <hi>Egypt</hi> lay in darkneſs. Heaven is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deſirable, but when the miſery threatned involves the contemners of it, they will appear bleſſed indeed, who ſought it, and obtain'd it. The various coming of our Lord doth ſhew the world the evil ſtate in which the unbelieving and rebellious ſinners are found, and ſo cannot but ſhew the good ſtate in which the faithful are found to be at his coming.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is ſomewhat of Royal prerogative in it: God will have his laſt coming to be the ſeaſon, becauſe it ſeems good to him that it ſhould be ſo.</hi> And this were reaſon enough, though there were no other; he hath reſerved times and ſeaſons in his own hand: and he who gives the reward freely, may (ſurely) chooſe the time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he will give it. <hi>That ever he will give, it is grace; that he will give it at laſt, is his pleaſure;</hi> of which none ever complain'd, when they received the bleſsing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There is much of Decorum, and due order herein: it would not be ſo ſeaſonable at any other time;</hi> their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is for the Lord their Maſter, and he is the fitteſt to view their Service, and to aſsign their recompence; they did not expect their happineſs before his coming, and yet they profeſſed they ſhould receive it at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and now when times and ſeaſons ſuit their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and declared hopes, there appears a juſt order and harmony between times and things: Now the promiſe, and their hopes are conſonant to each other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>There is ſomewhat of that we call neceſſary in the caſe, their happineſs is reſerved to that time, becauſe it could not be ſooner.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>All the greateſt good Gods Servants can receive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this coming of their Lord, is too little and mean to be their bleſſedneſs;</hi> beſides that, moſt of external advantages are the rewards of ſuch as ſhall never have better, and are given to hypocrites, Now 'tis neceſſary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49378:15"/>that faithful Servants ſhould ſtay till they may receive a better reward than hypocrites have.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>It is neceſſary all their work be done, before they receive their full bleſſedneſs; now their work ends not till they dye, then their works follow them, and they are bleſſed.</hi> It is not more neceſſary a Labourer do his work, ere he receive his wages; or a Soldier conquer, ere he triumph; than that the faithful Servants of the Lord do all their work ere they are bleſſed and fully recompenced for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Full bleſſedneſs of Gods Servants must be in a place and ſtate where all (not one excepted) may meet, and be joynt-heirs of the ſame inheritance.</hi> Now this cannot be in any place or ſtate, but that to which (at the Lords coming) they ſhall be carried. Now we come into the world, live a few days, and in ſmall numbers together, and cannot live all together, nor long together; your tears witneſs it: but we muſt be all gathered together ere all tears ſhall be wiped from all faces, and this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but where our Lord will be with us for ever, which will not, cannot be till his coming.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil death be conquered, and we raiſed immortal, which cannot be till the last coming of our Lord, we are not able to bear that glory which muſt be our final and full bleſſedneſs:</hi> none can ſee God while they live, mortal fleſh is too weak for immortal Glory, this is too weighty a Crown for heads that muſt lye down in duſt: We muſt dye, that we may be raiſed immortal, and ſo be made capable of our final happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lt.</hi> laſtly, in a word, <hi>The eternal Preſence of God with us in the immediate fruits of it, is our objective happineſs, and neceſſary to our reward; and this cannot be hoped or enjoyed whilſt we are on this ſide eternity,</hi> and are meaſur'd by time: But when the laſt coming of our Lord ſhall determine the periods of time, and fix our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49378:15"/>eternity, which ſhall commence at the expiration of time: Then he will never more be abſent from us, or hide his preſence, or abate it to us. This being neceſſary to our happineſs, it is neceſſary we ſtay until his laſt coming; wherein you will, I hope, and wherein I pray that you may meet the faithful and diligent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, his Stewards; wherein I perſwade my ſelf you will meet this faithful ſervant of Chriſt, whom you now lament, but ſhall then ever rejoyce with him. <hi>Sirs, I believe you will ſcarce doubt the truth I have preached; I am ſure you cannot with reaſon contradict it: I hope you will not through ſlothful hearts loſe the propoſed bleſſedneſs which is laſt, that it may be beſt to you.</hi> I have now done with all the Doctrinal part, and think I have ſpoken to as much as needed to be handled in it: I proceed to the Uſes of the Point; which I ſhall confine to theſe two following:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Information:</hi> Hence we may learn,
<note place="margin">1. Uſe. <hi>Information.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>That the care and buſineſs of Chriſtians is as their priviledg, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great:</hi> Happineſs in every condition and ſtate is an exceeding great priviledg; and to be faithful and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the Lords Family, according to our Talents and Relations, is no light and eaſy care, or work; it requires much wiſdom, and much heedfulneſs. I wiſh we were more apprehenſive of both, that our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be faithful might ſomewhat anſwer our hopes to be happy; if you ſeparate them now, God will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate you from them hereafter, when death ſhall cut you off from your opportunities, and Judgment ſhall cut you off from your hopes. Be holy, and ſerve your Lord, as ever you hope to be happy with your Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence learn, <hi>The firſt part of a faithful Servants and Stewards work is the more troubleſome, the laſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49378:16"/>part is moſt ſweet, and ſatisfactory; Sincerity and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence are ſweeteſt at laſt.</hi> The idle revelling Servant is moſt at eaſe when his Maſter is at fartheſt diſtance; but the diligent and faithful Servant doth moſt rejoyce when his work is neareſt an end, his Maſter neareſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his reward neareſt to his hand. All that is difficult, is at firſt ſomewhat harſh to our weakneſs; but when difficulties are well nigh conquered, it is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt quiet and ſatisfaction to the diligent hand, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind. <hi>Religion grows ſweeteſt to us at laſt, if we are ſincere in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence learn, <hi>That beſt men, though they ſhall be fully bleſſed at laſt, yet that laſt ſhall not be but when the Lord pleaſeth.</hi> None have our times in their hands, to prolong them, or ſhorten them to their humors or paſſions: Good Chriſtians ſhould live too little, and ſerve God and the Church too little, if bad men might meaſure out the time of their ſervice: ſuch men would ſend them to their happineſs ſooner than would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for thoſe that neeed them. And were our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival in glory at the diſpoſal of our friends, and ſuch as love us, we ſhould be kept longer from it than we would. It is fit it ſhould, and 'tis beſt that it be in God our gracious Soveraign and Lords hand, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out the time of our Service, and to fix the time of our reward, which ſhall be when he cometh; and he will come when he pleaſeth, and never to the loſs of his faithful Servants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence learn, <hi>To check the inordinate and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive grief or impatience of Spirit under our loſſes, in the death of our Relations.</hi> A thouſand diſputing thoughts will ſtart up in your breaſt, which muſt not be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:49378:16"/>any debate: It is the Lord who might have come ſooner, though we ſhould poſſibly think he came too ſoon; cruſh ſuch like ſurmizes, look rather to the known piety, diligence, faithfulneſs and labours of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Chriſtian Relations, and conſider to whom they lived Servants, to whom they are paſſed, with whom they now do, and ever ſhall live. <hi>Be followers of them, as they were of Chriſt; that in Gods time,</hi> i. e. <hi>the beſt and ſitteſt time, you paſs to them, and be with your Lord and theirs, in fulneſs of rewards and joys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly, <hi>By way of Exhortation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Uſe. <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
               </note> Since the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diligent Servant ſhall be bleſſed at his Lords coming; <hi>be perſwaded, all, whether Hearers or Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, eſpecially you who have ſuch examples, and who have a more peculiar concern in the occaſion of theſe lines; Be perſwaded to get ſuch a temper of ſoul, and lead ſuch a courſe of life, as may beſt become the Servants of ſuch a Lord who will come, and as may moſt comfort you when he cometh.</hi> I will not prolixly direct how you may thus do, nor farther move with argument; I will ſuppoſe you willing already, and deſirous to hear how you may be bleſſed in your temper, life and death.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Wiſdom is neceſſary; the verſe before my Text tells us as much, therefore you must get wiſdom from the Scriptures.</hi> Read, conſider and remember them, they are the rule our Lord hath left for direction of his whole Family: <hi>The entrance into theſe, giveth wiſdom,</hi> and this wiſdom will attemper both heart and life, that both may be holy, and the end happy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Settle your reſolutions to do all the known will of your Lord:</hi> Let it be your motive why you do,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49378:17"/>and your warrant when you have done the things that are proper to your places and callings. An unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved man will never be throughly faithful or diligent: the full purpoſe of your heart muſt be to do all the good to all as you can; which is the will of him who is good to all, and whoſe tender mercies are over all his works.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whatever advantage you have on men, whether it be advantage of Interest or Authority, uſe it all for God, and the good of their ſouls, who in likelihood will hearken to you, and be adviſed by you:</hi> Perhaps you may thus ſave ſome. Where you may forbid, let not ſin be committed, unforbidden: Where you may command let not good be omitted through want of your Command: uſe the Power God gives you to engage others to ſerve God. <hi>Abraham</hi> would command his Houſe to keep the Covenant of the Lord, ſo do you.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Watch over your ſelves, that you may watch over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and ere you pretend faithfulneſs to others, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and care to make them good, be ſure to be good your ſelves;</hi> none can believe you are in earneſt bent on the good of ſouls, if you neglect your own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Do the good which your places require, and then perſwade others to mind their Duty in their places. Maſters, Fathers, and Teachers will do more hurt by bad examples, than they can do good by beſt Counſels.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Look frequently to the future bleſſedneſs, under the conditions with which it is propoſed to you and others,</hi> in the Text, Context, and other places: <hi>a frequent view of that bleſſedneſs, will heighten your deſires and hopes: A frequent view of the conditions, will awaken your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49378:17"/>care, and provoke to diligence, leſt you ſhould come ſhort of your hopes,</hi> and be diſappointed of your beſt deſires. We are apt to forget our hopes, therefore look often to that bleſſedneſs; we are apt to indulge our eaſe and ſloth, therefore look well and often to the terms on which it muſt be expected. Though many weakneſſes are paſſed by and covered, yet wilful negligence and inſincerity will not be paſſed by; you muſt be faithful and ſincere, if you will be happy and bleſſed: <hi>This light is ſown for the upright; and the ſpirit in which is no guile, is, and ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> Pſal. 32.2.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Remember and imitate the beſt examples that fall under your obſervation.</hi> Beſide what are recorded in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, (to which you muſt look) it will be helpful to you, if you will remember and imitate thoſe whoſe life and carriage was much in your eye. And let me tell you, in the Copy our late faithful Brother ſet you, there are remarkable for your imitation. A prudent care to manage ſoul-concerns; a conſtant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied diligence in Labours for their good; an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dannted reſolution for known duty to God and Man; a tender and meek ſpirit, gently dealing with the weak, yet willing enquirers after God; A ready and full-willing mind to miniſter on every occaſion to the edifying of thoſe he converſed with: An even and ſteddy practice of what he commended as excellent or urged, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duty, an acquaintedneſs with the importance of duty and reward. A ſerious mindfulneſs of Death and Judgment, on which he diſcourſed frequently, and lively; dying to the World, but living to God, and ſtill valuing moſt what was ſo good, God would not, and men could not take from him: which appear'd in his deportment and frame of ſpirit, when loſs of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49378:18"/>Children, and uncertain riches, raiſed his eſteem and value of the Goſpel, and his and your hopes ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us in the Goſpel; a heart full of love, and thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for your good; whence thoſe laſt deſires and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in order to the promoting of your good, which I am informed he left you to conſider: <hi>Prize a Guide that will be faithful to your ſouls; keep the unity of the ſpirit into which you are called by the Goſpel; and ſeek God earneſtly for both.</hi> Now could we prevail with you who heard, and with others who read this diſcourſe, to endeavour for ſuch a frame of ſpirit, and to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, I know there would be more faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, diligence, and mutual hope among the Servants of the Lord, and his Family would be more beautiful in ſight of others, and more comforted and edified in their own ſouls. Read then, and read again, and be in your houſes (which ſhould be little Families, or Churches of God) in directing, and helping them to Heaven, what he deſired and labour'd to be amongſt you all; I do think he gave you the Copy of Faithfulneſs and Diligence, or I would not have thus ſet it before you; and I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to you as becomes both me and it, <hi>viz.</hi> It is the Copy of one who whilſt he was good, was ſtill a man; but though I could wiſh you would excel him, I will not flatter you with a hope you will do it; Oh that you would equal him, of whom allow me to ſay, He could do as much as moſt of beſt Men, Scholars, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Husbands, Fathers, Brethren, Miniſters; and his will was ever equal to his ability; the Service of his Lord was his life: though he lived not on it, he would not, he could not live without it; by a gracious Maſter fitted for, ſucceeded in, carried through much work in a little time; and I believe now rewarded with a Crown of Life and Righteouſneſs, which he knew he did not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49378:18"/>merit, though he knew it ſhould be his wages.</p>
            <p>In brief, he was ſuch an one as friends who knew him, deſire they may be; and now is ſuch as they hope they ſhall be; ſuch an one as ſome enemies already (as I am inform'd) have wiſht they might be, and others will once at laſt wiſh they had been. He had a worth known to himſelf, and others, but it did not puff him up. Should I ſay all I could, ſtrangers would think I exceed, Friends would know a better Orator might juſtifiably have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more. Yet once for all; If either Readers or Hearers carp at the Character I have given him, I have two things to ſay: Firſt it will be eaſier to quarrel at the praiſes, than to deſerve them: Next, I would defraud none of the Commendation due to them; nor do I prefer him above all; there are ſome (but too few) ſuperior in gifts and graces, I hope there are many his equals; I am ſure the moſt are lower by head and ſhoulders, who likelieſt to miſinterpret me, ſhall have a good wiſh for them, or rather a ſerious Prayer, teſtimony of a hearty love to their perſons, and unfeigned deſire of their own good, comfort and welfare; and of all theſe, to theirs, and the Church of God, in this, and after ages; for them I ſay, I will pray more days, fewer troubles, and that they may be in other things altogether ſuch as he was.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
